Well, we can ask yourself what is
what do you think mental strength is?
Does it mean doesn't Does it mean not
perceiving things that challenge you?
Or does it mean not being moved by the
challenges? So,
So,
does it mean Does it mean controlling
the environment so that it does not
bother you?
Or does it mean not being moved by the
environment that wants to bother you?
What would you think how to go about
developing that mental strength?
Could you develop mental strength of not
being bothered by the environment
um not being challenged by the things
that want to challenge you?
If your physical behavior is not kept in
check, if you act out of
the slightest pressure, the slightest
impulse, the slightest desire, if you're
unable to restrain it, if you're not
able to be patient about it, if you're
not able to endure it with the equally
unbothered mind.
So, uh it's important well, it's good
that you know, a person wants to be mentally
you know, a person wants to be mentally
strong. It's good that everybody strives
for that.
But it's important to to recognize the
right way of going about it because
if mental strength means not being
challenged by the things that want to
challenge you, well,
um physical desires, verbal desires,
things actions out of greed, aversion,
delusion are all forms of challenges
that the mind gives in to and acts out
of. So,
So,
uh usually people want to be strong
mentally in regard to things that cause
them suffering.
But they don't want to practice the same
mental strength in regard to things they
would want to
basically provide them with pleasure.
Such as such as central desires and so
on. But they're on the same footing. So,
But they're on the same footing. So,
whether you're challenged by
by something that wants to overwhelm you
with a grief
or you're challenged by something that
wants to overwhelm you with a thirst for
central pleasure, for tastes, touches,
and so on,
it's the challenge you're giving in to.
So, you cannot pick one
and then refuse the other because by
by giving in to the nature of being
challenged, you're pretty much um
surrendering yourself to the principle
of of of mind being overwhelmed by the
challenge coming from the world.
So, that's why if if if the if the um
if the mental strength is the importance
for you, is something that you want to
develop, then you have to uh equally
uh practice it in regard to things that
are pleasant and unpleasant.
And uh even things that are neutral,
obviously, that's the subtlest one
whereby you know, when there is seemingly no
you know, when there is seemingly no
challenge
uh pressuring toward the pleasure or
toward the pain,
the mind tends to turn kind of uh quite
easily to the uh distraction. That's
another kind of uh
It is subtler, but it's still another
way of giving in to the same principle.
So, because if you were not truly pressured
because if you were not truly pressured
by that neutral
neither pleasant nor unpleasant feeling
state of mind, well, you would be
perfectly at ease with it. You wouldn't
need to distract yourself from it.
So, that's that pressure of boredom that
we spoke about before.
So, mental strength then is developed on
the uh on the basis of these three feelings.
uh on the basis of these three feelings.
So,
in the pleasant feeling, uh you mustn't
be You mustn't give in to the challenge
for more pleasure.
In the unpleasant feeling, you mustn't
give in to the challenge for for for
getting rid of that discomfort.
And in the neutral feeling, you mustn't
give in to the challenge
for um
distraction and turning away from it,
for ignorance and indolence.
So, so that's how you develop mental
strength by um by keeping your behavior
in check
and then um enduring feelings on the
level of your mind, not acting out of
them, and certainly not losing the the
sight of them.